Alright, בוקר טוב Boker Tov everybody. בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף
Daf is צדיק ט', Tzadik Tes, 99. The odometer is almost about
to turn over. Okay, so anyway,
so we'll start at the top of the very first line of
צדיק ט'. Tzadik Tes. We're dealing with a contradiction in פסוקים Pesukim
about how high the דביר Dvir was, the קודש קודשים Kodesh Kodashim
in the time of שלמה. Shlomo. One פסוק Pasuk says 20 אמות,
Amot, the other indicates by talking about the whole בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash it sounded like it was 30 אמות. Amot. So the גמרא
Gemara says that the 20 אמות Amot is from the top of
the כרובים Cruvim upwards because basically you had the, well I don't
know if I want to erase this, but whatever.
There,
right, so you had here's the ארון, Aron, right, and here's the
כרובים Cruvim that were on the ארון. Aron. And in here's the
whole קודש קודשים Kodesh Kodashim which is 20 by 20 in the
time of שלמה. Shlomo. And שלמה Shlomo made these כרובים Cruvim here,
right, I guess they were standing like this with their wings like
that, or actually we're going to see one wing was, actually I
drew them incorrectly. They were standing like this.
Anyway, one wing was touching the wall there and one wing was
there, same here.
Okay, anyway, those were the כרובים Cruvim that שלמה Shlomo made and
they were standing on the ground. So they were 10 אמות Amot
high. So it says 20 אמות Amot when it's saying it's 20
by 20 by 20 rather than 20 by 20 by 30, it's
from the top of the כרובים Cruvim up where there was blank
space. Okay, so what's the point of measuring the blank space above
rather than the whole קודש קודשים? Kodesh Kodashim? So it said הא
קמשמע לן למטה כלמעלה, Ha Kamashma Lan Lemata Kelemala, that the space
below was like the space above. מה למעלה אין משמש כלום, Mah
Lemala Ein Mishamesh Klum, the same way above it's not functioning for
any object, it's completely empty, אף למטה אין משמש כלום, Af Lemata
Ein Mishamesh Klum,
even below it's as if it were not functioning for any object,
meaning it's as if it were empty. What does that mean? מסייע
ליה לרבי לוי, Mesayei Lei LeRabbi Levi, which supports the statement of
רבי לוי. Rabbi Levi. דאמר רבי לוי ואיתימא רבי יוחנן דבר זה
מסורת בידינו מאבותינו, DeAmar Rabbi Levi Ve'isayma Rabbi Yochanan Davar Zeh Masoret
Beyadeinu Me'avoseinu,
this is a tradition in our hands going back to our forefathers,
מקום ארון וכרובים אינו מן המדה, Mekom Aron Ve'Cruvim Eino Min Hamiddah,
and some don't have the word כרובים, Cruvim, אינו מן המדה, Eino
Min Hamiddah, excuse me, some don't have the word כרובים. Cruvim. The
place of the ארון Aron and the כרובים Cruvim are not part
of the measurement, which basically means that if you were to measure
from this wall to the ארון Aron here you'd measure 10 אמות,
Amot, and if you'd measure from this wall to the ארון Aron
here you'd measure 10 אמות, Amot, and somehow
magically you've got 20 אמות Amot plus the ארון Aron and the
whole thing is 20 אמות Amot and it somehow magically did
not take up any of the actual space. So and now I'm
making presumably the claim about the כרובים Cruvim as well because we're
measuring from the כרובים Cruvim above. So all of this stuff below
it actually didn't take up any space. Now I find that what,
like it's from another dimension. Yeah,
so that's interesting. Right, so I find that fascinating, right, because taking
up no space almost like suggests that it's like in some at
some level it's not present, it's not there. So what is the
idea of suggesting that the very thing that sort of like
represents God's presence is also like not taking up anything? I think
it speaks to another dimension. I think it's dealing with the basic
paradox
of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash in general, but specifically of the
ארון Aron and the כרובים, Cruvim, which is the whole point of
trying to sort of concretize God's presence. You know, when שלמה Shlomo
dedicates the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash he says, he makes this statement,
he says, אף כי השמים ושמי השמים לא יכלכלוך אף כי הבית
הזה אשר הכינותי. Af ki hashamayim ushmei hashamayim lo yechalkelucha af ki
habayis hazeh asher hachinosi. Right,
the heavens can't contain you God, you're
infinite, how are we supposed to understand the idea that there's this
finite house and space where you God will concentrate your presence? So
in a way it's I think what and particularly I think it
gets even more concretized when you start having the כרובים Cruvim here,
it starts feeling maybe a little uncomfortable, right, about these types of
like images, they feel almost like idols. I mean people deal with
that. What's the whole פשט pshat of the כרובים? Cruvim? So I
think it's like both sort of saying that to some degree this
is just a, there's no sense that God is really like,
it's impossible to imagine God
being limited himself and being more present in one place than in
another. That's the paradox. So to some degree they're there and they're
not there. You know, I think it's trying to strike on that,
to get to that theme. In contrast to that we had that
discussion of how all the dimensions inside the ארון Aron was so
detailed about how it had the measurements inside was so detailed. So
and then here it's to not even measured, right. It might also
be dealing with the reality that in the second בית המקדש, Beis
Hamikdash, you know, which was more approximate to them, there was no
ארון, Aron, which raises the question, does that mean that God's presence...
God's presence wasn't in the second בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash if there
was no ארון. Aron. So now if you're saying even in the
first בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash to some degree it was there and
it wasn't there, right, and nevertheless, God's presence doesn't require the physicality
of the ארון Aron is I think part of also sort of
like what's being addressed. But anyway it's a fascinating question like theologically
what is that supposed to get to. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara says like this: תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, it was
taught similarly: ארון שעשה משה יש לו רווח עשר אמות לכל רוח
ורוח. Aron she-asah Moshe yesh lo revach eser amot le-chol ruach ve-ruach.
If you measured it you'd get עשר אמות eser amot on each
side and the and somehow they're you know and the whole thing
from one end to the other would be עשרים אמות. esrim amot.
אמר רב חנא אמר שמואל כרובים בנס הן עומדים. Amar Rav Chana
amar Shmuel Keruvim benes hen omdim.
Now this is a sort of obviously a related statement but somewhat
independent because before we were making the statement about the ארון. Aron.
Anyway here it is the כרובים, Keruvim, it seems like somehow they
were magically there. Why is that true? שנאמר וחמש אמות כנף הכרוב
האחת וחמש אמות כנף הכרוב השנית עשר אמות מקצה כנפיו ועד קצה
כנפיו. Kene'emar: Ve-chamesh amot knaf ha-keruv ha-achat ve-chamesh amot knaf ha-keruv ha-shenit,
eser amot mi-ktzeh knafav ve-ad ktzeh knafav.
So it says each wing was חמש אמות, chamesh amot, right we
know there's עשר אמות eser amot here, okay, or whatever עשר אמות
eser amot to the middle. So if there's two כרובים Keruvim that's
עשרים אמות. esrim amot. But then but then how do you but
ten and five and five is ten and that gets you half
of it, but there's their body in the middle. So גופייהו היכא
הוו קיימי? Gufaihu heichi havi ka'imi? Where was their body? Right, if
each wing is חמש, chamesh, it's not עשר eser from one edge
to the other because you have to count the width of their
body in the middle. So
let's see, so what does he say? גופייהו היכא הוו קיימי? Gufaihu
heichi havi ka'imi? אלא שמע מינה בנס הן עומדים. Ella shema mina
benes hen omdim.
It must be that there was some miracle and the body similar
to what we just said before about the ארון Aron here too
their like body didn't take up any space. So מתקיף לה אביי,
Maskif lah Abaye, so אביי Abaye challenged this, this is not the
only way to resolve those פסוקים. pesukim. ודילמא בולטין כנרדא דגליא הוו
קיימי. Ve-dilma boltin ki-narda de-galya havu ka'imi.
Maybe it would be like a chicken, which I guess sort of
means I don't know you know the way a chicken's body is
down here and the wings are like I don't know I haven't
seen a lot of chickens in real life. My next door neighbor...
but anyway the wings are like up there, okay, I think is
the idea. So maybe here too you know maybe their bodies were
more like this and their wings were like that, okay, if you
just make their bodies horizontal, okay, so maybe they looked like that.
What, diagonal? More like this? Horizontal.
Whatever, same point. Instead of the wings coming... right, but the point
is the wings were coming out from a center point on the
back and it could be חמש אמות, chamesh amot, חמש אמות, chamesh
amot, עשר אמות, eser amot, their body didn't interrupt between the wings,
their body was below the wings. Okay, so that's not a problem.
מתקיף לה רבא ודילמא זה שלא כנגד זה הוו. Maskif lah Rava
ve-dilma zeh shelo kineged zeh havu.
Maybe they were not touching, maybe each one you know the body
with the wings was I don't know אחת עשרה אמה achas esreh
amah but the wings didn't touch in the middle, the wings sort
of like went side by side in the middle. Okay, so there
was an overlap if this is the ארון Aron here in the
middle, right, each one was the wingspan was עשר אמות, eser amot,
the body was let's say another אמה, אחת ama achas עשרה אמה,
amah, so each one went past the midpoint, right, if this is
the midpoint each wing went past an אמה amah past the midpoint,
but they didn't touch, they were like side by side. Okay. מתקיף
לה רב אחא בר יעקב, Maskif lah Rav Achai bar Yaakov, so
רב אחא בר יעקב Rav Achai bar Yaakov challenged this conclusion. Did
I skip a line? Yeah. ודילמא באלכסונא הוו קיימי. Ve-dilma be-alachsona havi
ka'imi. And that's what you have that nice picture for in the
רשב״ם. Rashbam. Who says that they were you know maybe they were
standing at a diagonal and their wingspans and bodies covered diagonally the
קדש קדשים, Kodesh Kodashim, not horizontally. So that gave you more space.
מתקיף לה רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע ודילמא בשמיא אעיל רווחא. Maskif
lah Rav Huna brei de-Rav Yehoshua ve-dilma be-shmaya ae'il ravcha.
That's echoing back a previous discussion. Maybe maybe the airspace above, at
the floor it was עשרים אמות. esrim amot. But the walls got
thinner as you went higher and maybe as you got higher the
walls were you know the air the the space was twenty-one or
twenty-two אמות. amot. What, so many קושיות kashyas here?
I know. מתקיף לה... like why they were so willing to accept
that the ארון Aron. בנס היה עומד, and now when you wanted
to sort of draw a similar conclusion about the כרובים, Keruvim, they
were like no no no there are other explanations. מתקיף לה רב
פפא ודילמא מיכף הוו כייפי ידייהו. Maskif lah Rav Papa ve-dilma michaf
havu chafi yadayu.
Maybe when their wings got towards the middle, you know if they
were like bent in, they weren't flat. So maybe when you're measuring
the חמש אמות chamesh amot you know you're measuring it like if
you imagine this is what the wing looks like, you the חמש
אמות chamesh amot of each wing include up to like the edge
but the wing wasn't straight. So therefore they were able to meet
in the middle.
Avi, you wanted to say something? You know these are all later
Babylonian אמוראים. Amoraim. Right. So there there might have been some shift
towards more rationalist explanations. Interesting, interesting, I got it. The earlier ones,
everything miraculous were all earlier. Well שמואל, Shmuel, this is all responding
to a statement in the name of שמואל, Shmuel, who was a
Babylonian... שמואל Shmuel was early. Yeah, okay. Shlomo built the כרובים Keruvim
of the ארון. Aron Right. The ארון Aron was משה. Moshe. Right.
So exactly. So maybe we don't want to just start expanding it
to everything. Like we see רבי יו. Rabbi Yo. Right. Okay. So
decide. מתקיף לה רב אשי ודילמא שלחופי הוו משלחפי? Matkif lah Rav
Ashi: Vedilma shalchufei havo meshalchefi?
Maybe they were sort of like... I didn't get exactly those ones.
How do they translate that? I mean the רשב"ם Rashbam sort of
says it's sort of like that you like clasp your hands...
crossed over. Crossed over? What does that mean? That they weren't like
this? But the פסוק pasuk describes them... Oh you mean, oh one
hand and the other crossed over. Oh it's a variation to be
side by side. As opposed to side by side, they were... they
overlapped. They overlapped because they were a little bit... a little like
not directly, you know, on slightly different planes. They weren't at the
same... so they were like that. Okay. כיצד הן עומדין? Keitzad hein
omdin?
Now, now as long as we're talking about the כרובים, Keruvim, let's
talk about where how they faced. Okay. רבי יוחנן ורבי אלעזר. Rabbi
Yochanan ve-Rabbi Elazar. Dispute of רבי יוחנן ורבי אלעזר. Rabbi Yochanan ve-Rabbi
Elazar. חד אמר פניהם איש אל אחיו. Chad amar: pneihem ish el
achiv. They faced one another, which is, you know, based on the
פסוק pasuk in... you know, in שמות. Shemot. וחד אמר פניהם לבית.
Vechad amar: pneihem labayit.
They faced towards the rest of the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, towards...
what? Right, towards the פרוכת. parochet. So למאן דאמר פניהם איש אל
אחיו הא כתיב פניהם לבית? le-man de-amar pneihem ish el achiv, ha-ketiv
pneihem labayit?
Now of course the פסוק פניהם לבית pasuk pneihem labayit is talking
about the כרובים Keruvim that שלמה Shlomo made that were on the
ground. And there, so obviously you can answer, the כרובים Keruvim on
the ארון Aron? faced one way, the כרובים Keruvim on the ground
faced another. But we want to understand that they're both the same.
So what do you do with that? So the גמרא Gemara says...
לא קשיא כאן בזמן שישראל עושין רצונו של מקום כאן בזמן שאין
ישראל עושין רצונו של מקום. Lo kashya: kan bizman she-Yisrael osin retzono
shel Makom, kan bizman she-ein Yisrael osin retzono shel Makom.
When ישראל Yisrael is doing what God, you know, God desired, so
the כרובים Keruvim faced one another to show sort of like... to
show, right, to show intimacy between the two of them, which represents
the intimacy between God and בני ישראל. Bnei Yisrael. And that's the
way משה Moshe made it. And when they don't... and then they're
not sort of... what do you call it... doing God's will, then
somehow they turn their faces and they sort of... they show that,
you know, it's like... it's like a couple that's having a fight.
You know, they're still living together, they're not getting a divorce or
whatever, but maybe they're like a little bit... giving each other the
silent treatment, not talking to one another right now. Okay, so therefore
they're not... stay... I understand, they're not facing one another. All right.
So that's how we would explain that. As Michael says, yes, you
could have imagined that the כרובים Keruvim are representing, I don't know,
somehow the divine and they're facing בני ישראל. Bnei Yisrael. But obviously
there's a problem there because there are two of them. So you
don't want the כרובים Keruvim to represent God. You want them to
represent the relationship. So the גמרא Gemara says... ולמאן דאמר... u-le-man de-amar...
in general you don't want it to represent God because then it
gets even closer to the whole problem about seeming like, you know,
a little close to be looking like an idol. So the גמרא
Gemara says, ולמאן דאמר פניהם לבית, u-le-man de-amar pneihem labayit, now if
you say that they were... they were fundamentally facing the בית המקדש,
Beit HaMikdash, right? So הא כתיב פניהם איש אל אחיו? ha-ketiv pneihem
ish el achiv? Doesn't it say that they faced one another? And
you don't want to say the same answer of whether עושין רצון
osin ratzon or לא עושין, lo osin, because if you emphasize פניהם
לבית, pneihem labayit, it says that that's the primary orientation. So you
don't want the primary orientation to be that they're לא עושין רצונו
של מקום. lo osin retzono shel Makom. So if the primary orientation
was לבית, labayit, what do you do with the fact that it's
also איש אל אחיו? ish el achiv? So it says, דמצדד צדודי.
de-mitzaddad tzadudei. You know, their faces are slightly at an angle. They're
looking at one another... they're facing out, but they're slightly tilted towards
one another. Yes. דתניא אונקלוס הגר אמר כרובים מעשה צעצועים הן. De-tanya:
Onkelos Ha-Ger amar: Keruvim ma'aseh tza'atzu'im hein. Because we learn in a
ברייתא, Beraita, אונקלוס הגר Onkelos Ha-Ger says, right, who is the translator
of, you know, of תנ"ך, Tanakh, כרובים מעשה צעצועים הן. Keruvim ma'aseh
tza'atzu'im hein. So quoting, it's interesting, this is not an Aramaic translation,
so it doesn't sound like they're quoting his translation. I mean, he's
emphasizing the Aramaic translation. Right, it's also he didn't translate כתובים, Ketuvim,
so he only translated נביאים, Nevi'im, and this is from כתובים. Ketuvim.
It sounds like he is just connecting, you know, this פסוק pasuk
to a... like about the פניהם איש אל אחיו. pneihem ish el
achiv. The other... this is a פסוק pasuk that again is about
the כרובים Keruvim and it says מעשה צעצועים. ma'aseh tza'atzu'im. So what's
צעצועים? tza'atzu'im? Like toys, right? But the רשב"ם Rashbam says here that
it means like the same way כרוב Keruv according to... if you
think about the, you know, the word "cherub", a cherub is like
a baby face. And according to some, that's the word כרוב Keruv
like the Aramaic word כרביא, keravya, like a baby, like a child.
Okay, so the מעשה צעצועים ma'aseh tza'atzu'im is also like child-like is
sort of how it's being read. הן ומצדדים פניהם כתלמיד הנפטר מרבו.
Hein, u-metzudadim pneihem ke-talmid haniftar me-rabbo.
So here is how... how does it become child-like, how's that relevant
for our discussion? So it says like a child that's sort of
leaving his master, that he's both like... you walk backwards and you
face your master, but you're also like halfway looking out the door
getting ready to run out to the playground. So therefore the כרובים
Keruvim are facing towards the בית, bayit, but they're also like a
little bit looking towards one another. Yes. And in the second temple
there were other כרובים Keruvim underneath those כרובים Keruvim or there was
no
ארון? Aron, Yeah, no, the second temple there was nothing there except
the... except the... what do you call it... except the stone, you
know, the אבן שתייה. Even Shetiyah. So this is all the first
בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. Yeah, okay, and there were no כרובים, Keruvim,
there was no ארון, there was just the אבן שתייה, Even Shetiyah,
which might be, like I said, the reason to be sort of
saying that even though... In the first בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash to
some degree they weren't really fully there either, you know. You couldn't
measure them. Okay, so now we continue. מי שיש לו בור לפנים
מבית חברו. Mi sheyesh lo bor lifnim mibeis hachavero. It's so funny
you know, we go back to earlier themes. We've been spending all
this time with things around מקח טעות mekach taus and then we
all of a sudden get back to okay, well when you said
x, what's included in x? That when you said you're selling a,
you're going to build a בית bayis or space for a בית,
bayis, how big? So now similarly we're getting back to the old
issue about getting an access road, you know, into your friend's field.
So remember we said before, if I sell somebody a, you know,
a well in my field there's a debate of בעין יפה מוכר,
be'ayin yafah mocher, בעין רעה מוכר, be'ayin ra'ah mocher, how much do
you implicitly, you know, is it implicit that you get an access
road as well? Here we're talking about let's say you did get
an access road. That was it, that was made explicit, okay, or
what some position that assumes that you get or you retain an
access road. How do you use that road? Because so let's take
a look. מי שיש לו בור לפנים מבית של חבירו. Mi sheyesh
lo bor lifnim mibeiso shel chavero. Somebody has a well in a,
or cistern, inside somebody's house. Okay, it doesn't only mean like behind
somebody's house, at least the way the רשב"ם Rashbam explains it, literally
means in the
house. Okay. נכנס בשעה שדרך בני אדם נכנסים ויוצא בשעה שדרך בני
אדם יוצאים. Nichnas besha'ah shederech benei adam nichnasim veyotzei besha'ah shederech benei
adam yotzim. You could only get your, have a right to demand
access to it during like normal hours when normal people are going
in and out of the house. Okay, it doesn't say when people
are awake, because you know they're allowed privacy too, right? So you
know if everybody's still getting up early in the morning or they're
going to sleep, you know it's late at night and they're, you
know, they don't accept guests at this time. So your hours are
when it's, you know, normally acceptable for people to come in and
out of the house. Okay. ואינו מכניס בהמתו
ומשקה מבורו. Ve'eino machnis behemto umashkeh miboro. And let's say you want
to have your animal drink some water. Hi everybody, it's me with
Bessie, I'd like to come in to your, to your well. No,
you don't bring your animals into the guy's house, even though you
have right to get to the well. אלא ממלא ומשקה מבחוץ. Ella
memaleh umashkeh mibachutz. So your rights are not absolute rights, okay? You're
still going into somebody's house, so therefore you'd have to fill it
up and bring it to your animal outside the house. And this,
bring friends apparently? What? No. I think that would obviously be not.
וזה עושה לו פותחת וזה עושה לו פותחת. Vezeh oseh lo posachas
vezeh oseh lo posachas. And there are two locks on the well.
The בעל הבית ba'al habayis has a lock and you have a
lock. So it's very interesting. You understand why you have a lock,
you don't want the בעל הבית ba'al habayis to be drinking from
your water, it's now your water. Why does, why does he have
a lock? Why is he trying to keep you out? So it
might be, the simple read of the משנה Mishnah is, so you
don't come in at times you're not supposed to, you know. So
if you always have to get him to take you to the
well, so then he's going to be controlling and making sure you
don't abuse your privilege. Okay, let's take a look at the גמרא.
Gemara. Inside the house, it sounds like. Inside the house? Yeah, well
look, we have running water in our house, you know.
But yes, it sounds like, I mean the משנה Mishnah is לפנים
מביתו. lifnim mibeiso. I, I would naturally assume it would be out
in the field behind the house, but the רשב"ם Rashbam consistently explains,
and we'll see in a, you know, that it does matter, could
just mean you have to get through his house to get to
the backyard, right? So it could mean behind, not inside. But לפנים,
lifnim, why do we think it's behind? Yeah I know, so that's
what the רשב"ם Rashbam says. רשב"ם Rashbam says it means inside the
house. No, no, why? Why don't we say it means behind? If
it said לפנים, lifnim, shouldn't it be in the front?
Like the yard or in the whatever? לפנים מהבית lifnim mehabayis
is that how you'd say in front of? לפני הבית. lifnei habayis.
No, but לפני ולפנים lifnai velifnim means more inner, right?
Not more in front. But no, נכנס לפני ולפנים nichnas lifnai velifnim
is you go more inside the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. The קודש
קדשים Kodesh Kodashim is לפני ולפנים, lifnai velifnim, more inner. Anyway, but
I think it's a question whether it means you only get through
the house and it's access in the backyard. The רשב"ם Rashbam says
it means in the house. Either way you have to get through
the house.
Okay, פותחת להיכא? Posachas leheicha? So where's what's the, what are you
locking? Maybe you're locking the front door? But no, אמר רבי יוחנן
שניהם לבור. Amar Rabbi Yochanan sheneihem labor. No, you're both, they're both
locks on the well. Cause maybe it's thought maybe the בעל הבית's
ba'al habayis lock was on his front door, which also could sort
of protect it, right? You can't get through the front door without,
to not, without getting the בעל הבית ba'al habayis to open up,
and he can't get to your well. So they could have been
on different locations.
So בשלמא בעל הבור בעא לשמורי מיא דבוריה. Bishlama ba'al habor ba'ei
leshamurei maya devorei. You understand the owner of the well, he's got
to protect the water of his well to make sure the other
guy doesn't steal what's now his water. אלא בעל הבית למה לי?
Ella ba'al habayis lamah li? Why does the בעל הבית ba'al habayis
need a lock on the well? אמר רבי אלעזר משום חשד אשתו.
Amar Rabbi Elazar mishum chashad ishto. So rather than just generally I
don't want you walking in my house, I don't want you having
an excuse to come into my house when I'm not around and
my wife is there alone and who knows you know what else,
what other designs you might have. Mostly for the guy? Presumably the
guy. Okay, but this guy now would you know, the bottom line
is you don't want somebody to have a regular license to walk
into your house when you're not around. Alright, so now the גמרא
Gemara says, next משנה. Mishnah. מי שיש לו גינה לפנים מגינתו של
חבירו. Mi sheyesh lo ginah lifnim miginato shel chavero. Similar story. I
have a garden, a vegetable garden behind your garden, and I again
have some right of access to my garden. נכנס בשעה שבני אדם
נכנסין Nichnas besha'ah shebnei adam nichnasin ויוצא בשעה שבני אדם יוצאין. veyotzei
besha'ah shebnei adam yotzin. Same story. I am allowed to go in
and out, but it has to be within normal business hours. ואינו
מכניס לתוכה תגרין. Ve'eino machnis letochah tagrin. I cannot go ahead and
take some merchants and say, "Oh, you're a tomato merchant, come, I'll
show you my tomato plants and we can make a deal, and
I'm going to sell you the produce of my garden." No, I'm
not allowed to have you cut through this other guy's garden to
get to my garden. It's only a right that I have. I
don't have a right to bring strangers, which might make it harder
for me to make a deal on my tomato plants. Okay, so
ואינו מכניס לתוכה תגרין Ve'eino machnis letochah tagrin ולא ייכנס מתוכה לתוך
שדה אחרת. Velo yikanes mitochah letoch sadeh acheret. I also can't say,
let's say I'm trying to go visit my friend David there, and
my garden is behind Michael's. So the best way to get to
David is to cut through Michael's garden, cut through my garden, and
then I'll be right at David's backyard. So why don't I do
it? I have rights to get to my garden and from there
I can get to a shortcut to my friend. No, I'm only
allowed access to my garden for the sake of my garden. So
even though I'm exactly doing what I'm normally allowed to do, obviously
I could lie, I could say I want to go check my
tomato plants, and once I'm there, then it's like people go to
the שול... shul... אשרי יושבי ביתך Ashrei yoshvei veitecha and then they're
able to use it as a shortcut. Using a שול shul as
a shortcut. So anyway, I could lie, but if I'm being honest,
then I only have rights to go through Michael's yard to get
to my garden for the sake of the garden, not to basically
just use it for other purposes as a shortcut. Okay, והחיצון Vehachitzon
now, זורע את הדרך. zorei'a et haderech. Now because it is not
my path, it's I have the right of access, but I don't
own the path. It's Michael's path. So Michael is entitled to plant
it. I can step on the plants, but he's entitled to plant
it. Okay, נתנו לו דרך מן הצד מדעת שניהם. Natnu lo derech
min hatzad mida'at sheneihem. Now let's say rather than giving me a
straight down the middle access, you went ahead and you
said... I'll erase my beautiful
כרובי... cruvy... and we'll say, let's say basically,
here was a garden, here was the other garden, whatever. And so
before we were talking about like I just cut straight in. But
instead, Michael said, "Look, please, don't cut straight in, it ruins my
grass, it ruins whatever. Why don't you go ahead and
take the sidewalk here? And if you take the sidewalk you sort
of can get to it like that." Okay. So I'm going to
take the sidewalk, I won't walk in anybody's yard, that's מן הצד,
min hatzad, makes me go out of my way a little bit
more, but it protects everybody's field.
Okay, so that's the... and I agree to that, it's מדעת שניהם.
mida'at sheneihem. Now this doesn't get to the idea, this doesn't get
to the discussion of let's say I don't agree to it, like
what sort of who's in a position to argue, is it by
default? I have a right to go as straight as
possible and then I have to agree to it? It doesn't make
that clear. But somehow we both came to the agreement, מדעת שניהם,
mida'at sheneihem, maybe when he was selling me this garden we agreed
that that would be my path. Okay, but we came to the
agreement that it would be a side path and therefore, and now
what that means is, because I agreed to that and I gave
up more direct access,
and we both agreed, it's not like I'm imposing on him my
right to cut through, which because I'm imposing on him, he fundamentally
has more full ownership of this and I just am demanding the
right to cut it. Here it's more like to some degree it's
been given to me, not fully, but like I agreed to the
side, I'm not imposing it on him, so I have a greater
sense of right, I wouldn't say ownership, but at least of right
in terms of a side path. Okay, so that's what the משנה
Mishnah says.
נתנו לו דרך מן הצד מדעת שניהם, Natnu lo derech min hatzad
mida'at sheneihem, נכנס בשעה שהוא רוצה nichnas besha'ah shehu rotzeh ויוצא בשעה
שהוא רוצה. veyotzei besha'ah shehu rotzeh. I can go ahead and go
there at any time. If I want to go at 3 AM
now, I'm going to use the sidewalk, I'm not cutting through your
garden.
I'm going at any time I want.
ומכניס לתוכה תגרין Umachnis letochah tagrin ולא ייכנס מתוכה לתוך שדה אחרת.
Velo yikanes mitochah letoch sadeh acheret.
Interestingly though, it still has the limit of I can't use it
סתם stahm as a shortcut. I have full rights, but it's still
for the purpose I don't own it, and it's still for the
purpose of the garden. Okay, so it's still like a different part
of my... this is like the public sidewalk? No, it's in your
yard. But it's more it's a path, whatever it is. וזה וזה
אינם רשאים לזורעה. Vezeh vezeh einam resha'im lezor'ah. In this case, I
can't plant it because it's still, as we were saying, Michael's path,
and he can't plant it though because it's more like I'm not
imposing it on him, it's more like I have more of a
sense of rights and ownership, and therefore that prevents him from planting
it because then I'm going to have to walk through his vegetables
or whatever it is, I want a clean path. All right, so
that's more of a stable sort of sense of right. Okay, so
let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל.
Amar Rav Yehudah amar Shmuel. אמה בת השלחין. Amah bat hashlachin.
Now we're going to talk about not a case of the משנה,
Mishnah, but once we're on this theme. Similar cases. So basically, if
somebody says to someone, I am selling you a irrigation canal, that's
an אמה, ama, so this is called an אמה ama because it's
an אמה ama deep, okay, so it's like, you know, it's like
a foot and a half deep. Okay, because we're going to see
it might be more than an אמה ama wide. I'm selling you
something to use for irrigating a בית השלחים, beis hashlachim, for irrigating
a field, okay, which you need a lot of water for that.
Okay, so in that type of a case, אני מוכר לך, ani
mocher lecha, נותן לו שתי אמות לתוכה, nosin lo beis amos letocha,
ואמה מכאן ואמה מכאן לאגפיה. ve'ama mikan ve'ama mikan le'agaseha. So there's
a
so I give in addition to the actual canal itself, which runs
through my yard, I give you שתי אמות. two amos. Now there's
a question if you read ואמה מכאן ואמה מכאן ve'ama mikan ve'ama
mikan is the next thing clarifying or adding. Okay, so one way
so let's first read it as adding. So here basically, here's your
yard, right, you've got, you know, you've got this canal that runs
through it here, with water or whatever, this irrigation canal that runs
through it with water, and you basically are selling that to me.
Okay, so in addition to selling the canal, you're also selling, it
says שתי אמות, two amos, right, an אמה ama on each side.
What's the purpose of selling that? This is this is now the
actual field itself. That's if ever there's a need to expand it.
That's the way the רשב"ם Rashbam says. I might need to expand
it to get more water to flow through or whatever. So in
addition to selling me the actual canal, you're selling me, you know,
or giving me the right to, maybe not selling me, but the
right to an אמה ama of ground on each side that I
can that I can expand it.
Plus, okay, this is if you read it as two separate things,
plus another אמה ama here and another אמה ama here so that
I can sort of stand, you know, here and actually do the
digging to expand it, or once I've expanded, stand here in order
to like access it. Okay, so that's if you read it as
two separate things. You get שתי אמות two amos for expansion, plus
another אמה ama on each side just for access. Okay, the other
way of explaining it is that it was really all saying one
thing. You get שתי אמות, two amos, i.e., an אמה ama on
each side. And that's an easier way to read it, and the
רשב"ם Rashbam prefers that second read. Okay, and i.e., an אמה ama
on each side in order to get access, which is more parallel
to our idea of the garden. That we're not talking about expansion,
we're just saying that's what you need for access. Okay, and it
doesn't mean you own it, it means like you have rights to
it. Okay, yes. Is it unusual that the ש"ס Shas didn't discuss
this case in the משנה Mishnah first? Yeah, I mean, sometimes the
גמרא Gemara doesn't have a comment on the משנה Mishnah and it's
really just continuing the conversation rather than rather than commenting, okay? If
I have a field adjacent to it or something? Yeah, right, presumably
you're going to or yeah, you know, you're going to draw the
water and then walk out of here and then go to your
field essentially. You know, yeah, although it is a big שלעפ, schlep,
you know, I'd rather just put in some pipes or whatever, but
I don't know if I could do that. Yeah, exactly. Are they
not discussing who owns the water in the yard? No, that's obviously
what I did, I bought the water. Okay,
so yeah.
Okay, now, אמה בית הקילון אני מוכר לך. ama beis hakillon ani
mocher lecha. Let's say you're saying it's a בית הקילון, beis hakillon,
which I don't know what the derivation of the word is, but
the רשב"ם Rashbam says it means that you're not going to use
the water to irrigate a field, you're going to use it for
drinking, for your drinking, for your animals' drinking, etc. I think that's
what he said.
Let me see or some has בית הסילון. beis hasillon. א סילון
A sillo is like a pipe, right? Is א סילון a sillo
a pipe? Steinsaltz says it's a Greek word which is a form
of pump. A pump? This is a channel that is filled with
a pump. Oh, interesting. Oh no, he doesn't say you drinking because
maybe it's not clean enough for you to drink, he says your
animals drinking and using it for like clothes washing is what he
says. Okay. All right. So anyway, so that you don't need as
much water. So in that case, נותן לו אמה אחת לתוכה, nosin
lo ama achas letocha, וחצי אמה מכאן וחצי אמה מכאן
לאגפיה. vechatzi ama mikan vechatzi ama mikan le'agaseha. Then maybe you don't
need, you know, again, one way of reading it is you only
have אמה ama אחת for potential expansion, not two, plus a half
אמה ama on each side for access. Or if you read it
the other way, it's saying you have a total אמה ama access,
a half אמה amah on each side. Okay, which is a little
funny because I guess maybe you just don't need maybe based on
the equipment you're bringing in, if all you're doing is getting smaller
quantities of water or you know whatever, maybe you don't need as
much access space to it. Okay, it's not exactly clear to me
why the quantity of water you're going to use determines how much
standing and access space you need at the edges, but I'm sure
there's some correlation there. Okay, so then it continues. Now, אותן אגפיה
נזרעים. otzo agaseha nizra'am. Now this gets back to the question of
our משנה, Mishnah, right? In our משנה, Mishnah, fundamentally, this was Michael's
field when I cut through it to get to my garden, I
was cutting through his field, so I didn't have a right to
plant that, I just had a right to cut through his field.
Okay, so what would you say here though? Okay, because here it's
more like a dedicated space directly connected to it, so maybe like
is that like the the cutting through the garden and that Michael
can plant it? Is that like the side path that neither of
us can plant? more dedicated to me, it's directly connected to the
to the canal. So הני צדי גפא מי זרעם? Hani tzadei gapa
mi zaraam? רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel, בעל השדה
זורעם. Baal Hasadeh zoraam.
Just like the cutting through the garden, okay, the owner of the
field has still owns that, and fine he's giving me right to
stand there to get my water but fundamentally it's his and he
can plant. רב נחמן אמר שמואל, Rav Nachman Amar Shmuel, בעל השדה
נוטעם. Baal Hasadeh notaam.
Now, not only that that it's fundamentally his right, but but the
question is what can he plant there? So one opinion says he
can plant seeds like vegetables and the other says he can plant
trees. And to me planting trees is a bigger חידוש chiddush because
it's harder for me to stand between trees that he's planted. But
the גמרא Gemara is going to make planting vegetables a bigger חידוש.
chiddush. מן דאמר זורעם, Man de'amar zoraam, the one that says that
he has the right to plant vegetables, seeds, כל שכן נוטעם, kol
shekein notaam, certainly you can plant them, plant trees. Why? We'll see.
ומן דאמר נוטעם, U'man de'amar notaam, but if you say you can
plant trees אבל זורעם לא, aval zoraam lo, he cannot plant vegetables,
why? חלחולי מחלחלי chilchulei mechalchali
because what they will do is that they will basically like, you
know, moisten the ground. Apparently the way I don't know somebody here
knows better about how these things work but, you know, apparently the
vegetables will draw water into, you know, from the canal. If these
are vegetables, draw water into the earth or and or maybe the
way I don't know that they go into the ground and they
cause more cavities then I don't know I mean and trees trees
put roots but according to the רשב"ם Rashbam apparently the roots go
more straight down I guess it depends on the tree. Anyway the
argument is that vegetables at the edge of a canal will cause
the canal's edges to be more, you know, delicate, less firm and
therefore might cause a collapsing of those edges. Okay, and that's not
going to be good for me if the edges of the canal
start falling into the canal. Also not only will it not be
good because it might get the canal dirty but it'll take away
my my, you know, my standing space if it actually causes them
to collapse which raises an interesting question which is if they collapse
do I get standing space then at the new edge of them?
Right? Is it to, you know, so that's like not fully spelled
out but it's interesting that the גמרא Gemara doesn't seem to be
bothered that if the guy's planting trees I'm not going to have
much of a space to stand. All right. חלחול המקום? Chilchul hamakom?
Right, like that's true, right, like shiver or something, to like tremble.
Okay. So all right, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay. All right fine. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. Now.
ואמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, V'amar Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel, אמת המים
שכלו אגפיה. Amat hamayim shekalu agapeha.
Now let's say it actually happened that these things collapsed. So now
again what I what I want to know is like I said,
do I have do I, you know, have I lost my standing
space? Is now my standing space at the new edge or I
say my standing space is now inside the inside the canal?
But anyway but it did collapse and the גמרא's Gemara question is
not where's my standing space, the גמרא's Gemara question is where am
I going to get the dirt to rebuild it? Okay. So מתקנה
מאותה שדה. Metaknah me'osah sadeh.
So you could actually say to the owner of the field, hey
buddy, you I'm going to get dirt from your field now and
use it to rebuild the edges of the canal. Why? How why
do I have a right to get dirt from his field? בידוע
שלא כלו אגפיה אלא באותה שדה. Beyadua shelo kalu agapeha ela b'osah
sadeh.
Because if those if those edge you know banks collapsed the dirt
found its way into this guy's field. They collapsed into the actual
canal and maybe they washed up at you know some other side
or something. So I don't know exactly understand, I mean I would
say to the bottom of the canal would be my feeling but
maybe at the end of the day, you know, I don't know.
Anyway, so there's some assumption that the dirt is somewhere to be
found in his field and therefore I'm entitled to rebuild them from
that dirt. So מתקיף לה רב פפא. Matkif lah Rav Pappa. רב
פפא Rav Pappa said ולימא ליה מיאך אשפלוה לארעאי, V'leima lei mayach
ashpluha l'arai,
which is exactly what I would say. Why doesn't the owner of
the field say to him what do you mean? Your water caused
them to collapse into your ground. The dirt is at the bottom
of the of the canal. What do you want to use my
dirt to rebuild the canal? אלא אמר רב פפא, Ela amar Rav
Pappa, שעל מנת כן קיבל עליו בעל השדה. She'al menat kein kibeil
alav ba'al hasadeh. It's always implicitly, the same way it was implicit
perhaps that I had a right to stand here although that was
not spelled out, is that implicit or not that gets back to
the question of עין רע ayin ra or עין יפה? ayin yafeh?
But anyway but somehow it was also implicit there's an understanding that
sometimes it collapses and the standard practice would be you'd be able
to use the dirt you would find in the field, you know,
obviously you couldn't go ahead and dig up the guy's vegetable garden
but to just סתם stam take some unused dirt, you know, you'd
be able to use that to to shore up the the edges.
Okay, so that was the issue about the access road which follows
a whole much earlier discussions. Again the order here is sometimes very
confusing about, you know, selling a well and having an access road
and here it's dealing with the rights of access. Okay now we're
going to continue with this discussion of access roads but for a
slightly different type of of a of an approach. Yes. Again this
is Babylonian אמוראים, Amoraim, irrigation canals were not in the גמרא. Gemara.
Yeah I was thinking about that, that all the irrigation canal might
be specifically to בבל. Bavel. Okay, so let's look at the next
משנה. Mishnah. מי שהייתה דרך הרבים עוברת בתוכה. Mi she'hayetah derech harabbim
overet b'tochah. Now,
I have in the middle of my field, I have a public
road going through my field, okay? I have a nice big you
know whatever, here here's my, you know this is my this is
my field. Basically there's two fields? Well yeah basically right. I've got
a big field, I've got a big wheat field and some highway
one runs right in the middle of my beautiful wheat field, okay?
So נטל ונתן להם מן
הצד. Natal venasan lahem min hatzad.
I'm saying I am sick of this, okay? This makes it impossible
for me to get good efficient farming done. What I'm going to
do is I'm going to take this over and I'm going to
assign the רבים rabbim you know something here at the edge. They
can still use my field but they'll use it at the edge
so it's not smack in the middle and I'm going to take
this again. Now, can you do it? So the רשב"ם Rashbam says
we're going to at least initially assume that I have, who who
do I negotiate with? The mayor? The רבים? rabbim? I mean right
who represents the רבים? rabbim? So interestingly the רשב"ם Rashbam says the
initial assumption here of the גמרא Gemara at least is that I
sort of have a right to do it because since I don't
have anybody else to negotiate with and we sort of say we're
assuming now the type of like a זה נהנה וזה לא חסר,
zeh neheneh vezeh lo chaser, you know, so you know, so it
doesn't hurt them, they get one, it's hurting me that it's in
the middle, for them it shouldn't matter. So that maybe I have
a right to just go ahead and sort of do it on
the assumption that it's not hurting them and therefore I'm, you know,
they're auto- you know, it's not a problem that they're not officially
represented because we will objectively assume that they're sort of not being
hurt in this, which is a funny idea, right? Still making a
decision for people who are not represented. Yes. How does something become
a רשות הרבים reshus harabim in the first place? Like here, you
know like the government comes in and builds a road or something
like that. Right, no I mean... Right, so that's true, right? How
does it become an official רשות? reshus? So that's not clear. So
the רשב"ם Rashbam has some possibilities, right? If you take a look
at the רשב"ם: Rashbam: מי שהייתה דרך הרבים עוברת בתוך שדהו. Mi
shehaisa derech harabim overes besoch sadeihu. So it's a good question. Let's
see the possibilities he has. שהוחזקו לעבור שם מעולם, Shehuchzeku la'avor sham
me'olam,
right? So let's say, you know, whatever, for you know, for age
immemorial, this has been a path, okay? And you know, so whatever
it is, like, you know, it's not like it started with my
field and then they imposed themselves, this always was the arrangement. Okay,
או על ידי בעל השדה שנתן להם מתחילה הדרך. O al yedei
ba'al hasadeh shenasan lahem mitechila haderech. Or I made some arrangement with
the town hall or something, which is funny because then it does
sound like there is somebody to make an arrangement with. Okay, but
anyway, or maybe I was a צדיק, tzaddik, you know, some people
came to me and they said it would be so much easier
if we could get to the other side if we could cross
through and I started saying yes and next thing I knew everybody,
I don't know. But anyway, but the interesting point where the רשב"ם
Rashbam assumes that I have the right to do this without somebody
representing the other side is he invokes the principle of כופין על
מידת סדום. kofin al midas Sedom. כופין על מידת סדום Kofin al
midas Sedom means a case of זה נהנה וזה לא חסר. zeh
neheneh vezeh lo chaser. Like can you force somebody, like you know,
to give something if it's like not hurting him, you know, I
don't know. Let's say I've got a nice fire here and we're
in the campsite right next to you, right? You're in the campsite
right next to me and you're having a hard time, you don't
have any matches, you're having a hard time getting a fire started.
So you say, can we just put like a stick here, like
to just, you know, to get a fire started? I say, no.
Okay. So,
so the question of כופין מידת סדום kofin midas Sedom is like
do you force me like to allow the other person, like in
a בית דין, beis din, could a בית דין beis din force
me to allow them since it doesn't hurt me at all and
they benefit? Okay, so that's the, so the רשב"ם Rashbam says well
maybe it's a similar idea. Nobody represents the רבים rabbim and since
in principle we would force somebody to do something that nobody loses
from, so you know, on the other side benefits, we'd for- so
we're going to allow this guy to make this deal almost unilaterally.
Of course it's a little different, right? Taking a fire from me,
I really didn't lose anything, I you know, as in this case
you took one thing away and gave me another thing. It's not
the exact classic מידת סדום. midas Sedom. Yes, Tace. Wait, is it
not the move around? So the גמרא's Gemara going to get to
that. How is it so clear that nobody's hurt by this? Right?
So exactly, exactly, so we're going to get to that. Yeah. Yeah,
I'm going to add that too. But the other, my other question
is, you know, it's a comment, sort of. It seems to the
רשב"ם Rashbam it makes no difference which was there first. In other
words, certainly I can understand if it was my field and I
gave them the דרך, derech, I could potentially, okay, now I'm going
to move it. But if the דרך derech was always there then
it was a field, two sides surrounding it, I still have the
same right even though it was always there. Right, so correct. So
the big question to ask is that do I fundamentally have a
right or not? But let's look at the continuation of the משנה
mishna because the משנה mishna continues and says: מה שנתן נתן ושללו
לא הגיעו. Mah shenasan nasan veshello lo higio. What you gave them,
you gave them, thank you very much, we now have that road,
and what was yours didn't reach you, but you were not able
to reclaim what you wanted as the middle one. Okay, so at
the end of the day you lost on that whole deal. So
you don't have to argue why it's legitimate. It's quite the opposite.
It sounds like the deal wasn't legitimate. But one way or the
other, you're going to say if the deal was legitimate, then why
don't I get the road I was trying to get? And if
the deal wasn't legitimate, why do I lose the new road I
gave them? Okay, but clearly the argument here is that it wasn't
legitimate because it didn't work. And even before they've walked on it?
Like I knew this right away or... Well we'll see, okay so
we'll see. דרך היחיד ארבע אמות דרך הרבים שש עשרה אמה. Derech
hayachid arba amos derech harabim shesh esrei ama. Now, let's say I
actually, it's not exactly clear what the context will be, but let's
say the context is selling. I'm going to sell Michael a path
through my field and we'll call it a private path. So then
it has to be four אמות amot wide. If I'm making some
deal with City Hall and agreeing to sell them a public path
through my field, a road through my field, it has to be
16 אמה wide. Okay, so the reason for four אמות amot is
apparently you need four אמות amot to get a wagon through, but
that's just for individual. וכמושב אדם? u'chmoshav adam?
Yeah, but anyway the רשב"ם Rashbam references the idea of a wagon.
Anyway, okay, so now, דרך הרבים. Derech harabim. Now, דרך המלך, Derech
hamelech, if it is the King's Highway, דרך המלך נלך. Derech hamelech
neilech. Apparently there actually was in an ancient- in the ancient world,
a highway called the King's Highway which is the דרך המלך. Derech
hamelech. דרך המלך אין לה שיעור. Derech hamelech ein lah shiur. That
has no limit. Now what does that mean? It means if- if
I make an arrangement with the castle there to sell a King's
Highway through my path, he gets everything? So this seems to no
longer be about מקח וממכר. mekach u'mimkar. This is saying a different
הלכה. Halacha. The king is passing through town, he's allowed to go
however the heck he wants and nobody- and the- and even the
גמרא Gemara says like if I- if the short way for me
to get where I'm going if I'm the king, of who was
it, it's good to be king, was that from Mel Brooks? It's
good to be king. Anyway, if I have to get from here
to there and your- your store is in the way or your
little food cart is in the way, it's like sorry for your
store and I'm just taking my troops or whatever, we're just bursting
through and we're doing the shortest path and we're going wherever we
want. And he can't decide, I want to go that way because
it's more scenic? I don't know. Okay, now דרך הקבר, Derech hakever,
similarly, if people are going to bury a body, אין לה שיעור.
ein lah shiur. Also there is no limit. Now again what does
that mean? So the רשב"ם Rashbam says it might mean the same
idea that they're passing through town and you can't sort of say
stay off my field, like they can you know, go through anybody's
field that they need to to get to the grave. But he
says if that's what it means, he says then it would not
be the same as a king, they wouldn't have the right to
like knock down a building. They would have the right to like
walk over grass or walk over wheat and like so you know,
to maybe trample on some property that way, but not to actually
destroy a structure. But that's interesting, like if people are going to
grave have some just fundamental right to you know, to not- sort
of like now, you know, you get the- you they- you put
on your- your you know, your brights and you know, sometimes you
get the police to help you like get through traffic or whatever.
So a little bit like that, okay, they can sort of go
whichever way they want and the shortest way. Like a police escort.
Yeah, okay. The other explanation of the רשב"ם Rashbam though is- is
that it basically is that like somebody's got a you know, they
had these family plots and we're going to get to them, these
family caves. And somebody's got a family cave and this is more
similar to the earlier discussion that's like behind my field. So- and
then you know, I sell them basically the- now the question is
did I sell them the right? I have to check whether he
says I sold them the right or they have the right. Hold
on, let me just check. He says המוכר
דרך קבר לחברו, hamocher derech kever lachaveiro, right, so I sell them
the right to get through my field to get to their family
grave, to their family you know, the cave there, their ossuary, is
that what it's called? Is that- what is an ossuary? Anyway, and
in that case as opposed they can go with as many people
as they want, like you know, if they want to go a
hundred people wide to get through once they bought that right, so
then it's a specific case where I sold them a דרך הקבר
derech hakever and then there's no limit to the amount of people
that they can have passing through and how wide that can be.
Okay? Now what? דייני ציפורי אמרו Dayanei Tzipori amru, בית- I'm sorry,
שיעור מעמד. Now how about for the standing, the space that you
have to stand to greet the mourners after the burial? So דייני
ציפורי Dayanei Tzipori אמרו, amru so the judges of Tzipori, the רשב"ם
Rashbam says I don't know who they are, says בית ארבע קבין.
beit arba kavin. ובית ארבע קבין. u'veit arba kavin. Six קבין kavin
a בית סאה beit se'ah is 50 by 50 אמות. amot. Okay,
that's a בית סאה beit se'ah and a סאה se'ah is six
קבין. kavin. So this- so it is two thirds of this. Okay,
so this is- if this is two קב kav and this is
four קב, kav, okay, so it's 50 by 50, it's two thirds
of 2500 square אמות, amot, so you can do the math. Okay,
that's בית ארבע קבין. beit arba kavin. We will see about that.
So the גמרא's Gemara going to get because of the end of
this into issues about burial. So that's where some of the next
גמרא's Gemara going, but first we're going to address the beginning of
the משנה. Mishnah. Yes, Michael. For the קבר, kever, you know, I
understand they can take as much space as they need but like
you know, should they- do they לכתחילה lechatchila should- try to be
sensitive? Yeah, I don't know. Okay, let's look at the גמרא. Gemara.
Yeah? So the king can build
whatever thoroughfare he wants to go anywhere he wants at any time
for any reason? Right. So יאשיהו Yoshiyahu didn't follow הלכה halacha when
he tried to keep the king of Egypt. There you go. Okay,
he can- we're talking about within his own country. אמר רב יהודה
אמר רב. Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav. Now we're going to get
to the core of this משנה. Mishnah. Why, assuming that this was
a legitimate transaction and they got this new road, why did- he-
was he not able to- to reclaim his right? Okay, לנקוט פירזא
ולתיב? Linhot pirza u'leitib? Now if you say that the reason is
is that legally he does now own this road, the- the old
one, but you know, the רבים rabim are just continuing to use
it, so he just can't protect it. So- since when can he
not protect his own property? They now... own this, this is now
his, let him take a pitchfork and sit in front of it
and prevent people from using it. Why can't he reclaim it? So
should we say שמע מינה לא עביד איניש דינא לנפשיה, shma mina
lo avid inish dina linafshei, should we say even
במקום דאיכא פסידא? bimkom deika psida? Should we say that you're not
allowed to take the law into your own hands even if there's
a loss? Because remember back in בבא קמא, Bava Kamma, there's a
question: are you allowed to take the law into your own hands
to prevent loss and so on? And everybody said when it's about
protecting your own property and preventing loss as opposed to like if
you already stole from me, for me to break into your house
and take it back is a different story, but for me to
protect my property and protect myself from suffering loss, I'm allowed to
defend myself and my property. So why can't the guy just stand
here and prevent people from using it? Okay, so assuming that it
was a good transaction. So אמר רב זביד משמיה דרבא, Amar Rav
Zevid mishmei deRava, גזירה שמא יתן להם דרך עקלתון. gezeira shema yitein
lahem derech akalton. So it really wasn't a good transaction. Okay, why
wasn't it a good transaction? Because we're afraid that even though it
looks like he gave them an equivalent road, we're afraid that either
this time or next time or whatever, if we allow people to
do this, it might turn out that this was actually a twisted
road, it wasn't as convenient, and therefore we're going to invalidate all
such transactions, presumably since there's nobody representing the other side. If there
was somebody representing the other side, then they could check it out,
right, and so on. Yeah, they should've done it on both sides.
Okay, well, okay, so obviously that's going to be the next question.
But the first thing is to say why it's illegitimate. So the
point is because it's unilateral, it could be abused, the transaction. And
therefore it might turn out to be a non-straight path and therefore
we have to invalidate the transaction. Okay, רב משרשיא משמיה דרבא אמר
בנותן להם דרך עקלתון. Rav Mesharshiya mishmei deRava amar binosein lahem derech
akalton. His answer really is quite different. It sounds very similar, but
it's quite different. He actually says no, actually, the transaction normally would
be fine and they would get this and you'd be entitled to
reclaim this. He actually allows for a case that's very different from
the משנה. Mishna. The משנה Mishna is talking in a circumstance where
you did not give them an equivalent road. But if you gave
them an equivalent road, it's completely legitimate, they get the new one,
you get the old one. Okay, but he's not the position we're
going to focus on. We're going to focus on the position that
says it's never good. רב אשי אמר, Rav Ashi amar, and here's
Michal your point, רב אשי Rav Ashi says כל מן הצד דרך
עקלתון היא. kol min hatzad derech akalton hi. Any other road is
an out-of-the-way road for someone, okay? קרובה לזה ורחוקה לזה. kerova lizeh
verachoka lizeh. Any change, people are always going to resist change, okay?
So therefore, you know, now I guess it's true that if the
entire city lives over here, then it's possible to give a road
that's better for everyone. But the point is under normal circumstances, any
change is going to hurt some people and help other people. So
therefore, what? Some people on the other side to get through. Exactly.
For the people who live here it's a worse road, and for
the people who live here it's a better road, right? Just do
it in the beginning where the road was built first. Right. Yes,
any road, right, that's true, but any change is hurting a certain
segment of the population. So therefore you can't make a change unless
again you have a mechanism of representing the entire community, right, and
you actually have a bilateral transaction. But any unilateral transaction, unless it's
completely, you know, we normally have to assume that you can't do
a unilateral transaction because there's some people that are going to be
hurt. So therefore either we're concerned it will be clearly out of
the way or by definition it'll always be considered to be not
good for everybody and therefore illegitimate. So the transaction was not legitimate.
So fine, the transaction was not legitimate, I get why they still
have this road. Give me back my road, okay? And that's going
to be now the next question. The רבים rabbim should not resist.
Right. Well, that might more be like the דרך המלך. derech hamelech.
This is a יחיד. yachid. If you have the דרך המלך, derech
hamelech, it's a different story. Okay, now. So הגמרא haGemara says ולימא
להו—so velima lehu let's just get a little bit more—ולימא להו velima
lehu שקלו דידכו והבו לי דידי. shaklu didchu vehavu li didi. Fine.
You want to say that the whole transaction because it was unilateral
was illegitimate? Fine, take back your road, give me mine back. So
הגמרא haGemara says המני רבי אליעזר היא, Hamani Rabbi Eliezer hi, דתניא
רבי יהודה אומר משום רבי אליעזר רבים שביררו להם דרך לעצמם מה
שביררו ביררו. detanya Rabbi Yehuda omer mishum Rabbi Eliezer rabbim shebereru lahem
derech le'atzmam mah shebereru bereru. So if the רבים rabbim decide to
take a path for themselves, they have a right to take that
path. Eminent domain. So first of all, but even better, you're giving
them the path. Of course the question is what does that mean?
The רבים rabbim can just all of a sudden start trampling through
somebody's yard and decide they're going to do that? So הגמרא haGemara
says רבים, rabbim so הגמרא says ורבי אליעזר רבים גזלנין נינהו? veRabbi
Eliezer rabbim gazlanin ninhu? What, the רבים rabbim are גזלנין? gazlanin? They
can just סתם stam go ahead and start trampling and it becomes
theirs? אמר רב גידל אמר רב כגון שאבדה להם דרך באותה שדה,
Amar Rav Gidel amar Rav kegon she'aveda lahem derech be'osa sadeh, that
they lost a path in the field. So basically in a different
scenario. The רבים rabbim, had a path through my field. It was
a rainy season or whatever, the path got washed away. Okay, and
now they want to start going through the field again and they
had rights for a certain path but they can't find where it
was. So they're now allowed as a רבים, rabbim again, I don't
know how they do it, they take a vote, to default by
how they start. but whichever path they now decide to start going
through my field, right? That will now be their new path, okay?
Obviously they can't just סתם stam walk through my field, but if
they always had a path and they can't figure out which, whichever
one they choose, which the word בירור berur now makes better sense,
they selected a path because they did have rights to a path,
it's legitimate. Fine, that's רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. What does that have
to do with this case? This case they still have their old
path. Why do they get rights to a new path? Okay, so
this stays the גמרא Gemara is thinking that because at an initial
stage I said to them use this path, that's somewhat analogous to
them, you know, trying to reclaim an old path, although there's a
big difference. I don't understand it at all. I gave it to
them with the assumption that I was getting this back, and they
still have this. So why does that give them rights, you know,
to this thing here on the side? So it's not at all
clear why they should have that. Also, Michael's question is, did I
just say the words? Did they start using the path? That right
now the comparison to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer seems very weak and
we're still like left with this question about like why do the,
if this, if they still have this and it wasn't a good
sale, what gives them rights to that? So we will end here
today and we will have you with a cliffhanger here to tomorrow
find out why it is that the רבים might still get both
paths. Okay? We could have concluded in a minute. What? The first
answer was that fundamentally they were looking at each...